<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" >

<!--
Layout borrowed from Doug's smartmontools_scsi.xml.  The following text
is also from his file.

This is DocBook XML that can be rendered into a single HTML page with a
command like 'xmlto html-nochunks <this_file_name>'.  It can also be
rendered into multi-page HTML (drop the "-nochunks") or pdf, ps, txt,
etc.
-->

<article id="index">
 <articleinfo>
   <title>FAQ - Frequently Asked Questions</title>
   <author>
    <firstname>smartmontools</firstname>
    <surname>developers</surname>
    <affiliation>
     <address>
      <email>smartmontools-support@lists.sourceforge.net</email>
     </address>
    </affiliation>
   </author>
  <authorinitials>sd</authorinitials>
  <pubdate>2003-09-24</pubdate>

  <revhistory>
     <revision>
       <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
       <date>2003-09-24</date>
       <authorinitials>sd</authorinitials>
       <revremark>
             Moved from index.html to XML
       </revremark>
     </revision>
  </revhistory>

  <copyright>
   <year>2003</year>
   <holder>Bruce Allen</holder>
  </copyright>

  <legalnotice>
   <para>
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
      Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software
      Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts,
      and with no Back-Cover Texts.
   </para>
   <para>
    For an online copy of the license see
    <ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/fdl.html">
    <literal>http://www.fsf.org/copyleft/fdl.html</literal></ulink> .
   </para>

  </legalnotice>

  <abstract>
  <para>
   FAQ - Frequently Asked Questions
  </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>

<!--
<toc></toc>
-->


<sect1 id="a">

<title>What do I do if I have problems, or need support?  Suppose I want
to become a developer, or suggest some new extensions?</title>

<para>First, search the support mailing list archives to see if your
question has been answered.  Instructions are in the following
paragraph.  If you don't find an answer there, then please send an
e-mail to the smartmontools-support mailing list.  Instructions are
available at <ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/smartmontools-support">
<literal>http://lists.sourceforge.net/mailman/listinfo/smartmontools-support</literal></ulink>
. The list is moderated but you're not required to subscribe to it in
order to post your question.</para>

<para>To search the archives, first go to <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=smartmontools-support">
<literal>http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=smartmontools-support</literal></ulink>
. In the top left corner you will see a search box: use <emphasis
role="bold">Mailing List</emphasis> as the type of search.  This tool
works very well.</para>

<para>Note that from time to time SourceForge has mailing problems and
you'll get a message telling you that <emphasis role="italic">Either
your mailing list name was misspelled or your mailing list has not been
archived yet.  If this list has just been created, please retry in 2-4
hours</emphasis>.  If this happens, you'll have to try again
later.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="b">

<title>What are the future plans for smartmontools?</title>

<para>My plan is that smartmontools-5.x will support ATA/ATAPI-5 disks. 
Eventually, we'll do smartmontools-6.x to support ATA/ATAPI-6 disks,
smartmontools-7.x for the ATA/ATAPI-7 standard, and so on.  The "x" will
denote revision level, as bugs get found and fixed, and as enhancements
get added.  If it's possible to maintain backwards compatibility, that
would be nice, but I don't know if it will be possible or
practical.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="c">

<title>Why are you doing this?</title>

<para>My research group at U. Wisconsin - Milwaukee runs a beowulf
cluster -  <ulink url="http://www.lsc-group.phys.uwm.edu/beowulf/medusa/">
<literal>http://www.lsc-group.phys.uwm.edu/beowulf/medusa/</literal></ulink>
-  with 600 ATA-5 and -6 disks (300 IBM and 300 Maxtor).  We have more
than 50 TB of data stored on the system.  I also help out with a cluster
-  <ulink url="http://pandora.aei.mpg.de/merlin/">
<literal>http://pandora.aei.mpg.de/merlin/</literal></ulink> -  at the
Albert Einstein Institute that has another 300 IBM ATA-6 disks (36 TB
total).  It's nice to have advanced warning when a disk is going to
fail.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="d">

<title>I see some strange output from smartctl.  What does it
mean?</title>

<para>The raw S.M.A.R.T. attributes (temperature, power-on lifetime, and
so on) are stored in vendor-specific structures.  Sometime these are
strange.  Hitachi disks (at least some of them) store power-on lifetime
in minutes, rather than hours (see next question below).  IBM disks (at
least some of them) have three temperatures stored in the raw structure,
not just one.  And so on.  If you find strange output, or unknown
attributes, please send an e-mail to the mailing list and we'll help you
try and figure it out.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="e">

<title>What Kernel Version is needed? (Linux)</title>

<para>Kernel versions 2.4.0 or later should work.  We recommend the
latest 2.4 kernel.</para>

<para>Vanilla kernel.org 2.2.X kernels do not support the
HDIO_DRIVE_TASK ioctl(), which is needed for the ATA drive to execute
the ATA SMART RETURN STATUS command.  So these kernels will not
work.</para>

<para>Vendor-supplied 2.2.X kernels, and vanilla 2.2.X kernels patched
with Andre Hedrick's IDE patches -  <ulink url="http://www.funet.fi/pub/linux/kernel/people/hedrick/ide-2.2.20/">
<literal>http://www.funet.fi/pub/linux/kernel/people/hedrick/ide-2.2.20/</literal></ulink>
(also available from your local kernel.org mirror, not updated for
2.2.21 or later, and probably still containing a few bugs) may support
the needed ioctl().</para>

<para>If the configuration option CONFIG_IDE_TASK_IOCTL exists in your
2.2.X kernel source code tree, then your 2.2.X kernel will probably
support smartmontools.  Note that this kernel configuration option does
<emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis> need to be enabled.  Its presence
merely indicates that the required HDIO_DRIVE_TASK ioctl() is
supported.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="f">

<title>What attributes does smartmontools not yet recognize?</title>

<para>From Maxtor disks (99), (100), (101)</para>

<para>If you can attach names/meanings to these attributes, please send
a note to the mailing list.  If you have access to other SMART utilities
(especially manufacturer-specific ones, see below) and can send us
comparison output from smartctl and the other utility, that's especially
useful.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="g">

<title>My Maxtor/Hitachi/Fujitsu disk is only a few days old, yet
smartctl reports its age (Attribute 9) as thousands of hours!</title>

<para>On some recent disks, Maxtor has started to use Attribute 9 to
store the lifetime in minutes rather than hours.  In this case, use the
-m option (smartctl versions 5.0.X) or the --vendorattribute=9,minutes
(smartctl 5.1.X) option to correctly display hours and minutes.</para>

<para>Some models of Fujitsu disks are known to use Attribute 9 for
lifetime in seconds.  In that case, use the --vendorattribute=9,seconds
option to correctly display hours, minutes and seconds.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="h">

<title>The power-on timer (Attribute 9 raw value) on my Maxtor disk acts
strange.</title>

<para>There are three related problems with Maxtor's SMART
firmware:</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">1 - </emphasis>On some disks from 2001/2002,
the raw value of Attribute 9 (Power On Time) is <emphasis
role="italic">supposed</emphasis> to be minutes. But it advances at an
unpredictable rate, always more slowly than one count per minute.  One
(unconfirmed) theory is that when the disk is in idle mode, the counter
stops advancing.  This is only supposed to happen in standby
mode.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">2 - </emphasis> In Maxtor disks that use the
raw value of Attribute 9 as a minutes counter, only two bytes (of the
six available) are used to store the raw value.  So it resets to zero
once every 65536=2^16 minutes, or about once every 1092 hours.  This is
fixed in all Maxtor disks manufactured after July 2003, where the raw
value was extended to four bytes.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">3 - </emphasis> In Maxtor disks that use the
raw value of Attribute 9 as a minutes counter, the hour time-stamps in
the self-test and ATA error logs are calculated by right shifting 6
bits.  This is equivalent to dividing by 64 rather than by 60.  As a
result, the hour time-stamps in these logs advance 7% more slowly than
they should.  Thus, if you do self-tests once per week at the same time,
instead of the time-stamps being 168 hours apart, they are 157 hours
apart.  This is also fixed in all Maxtor disks manufactured after July
2003.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="i">

<title>Where can I find manufacturer-specific disk-testing
utilities?</title>

<para>A good listing of such utilities can be found at <ulink url="http://www.benchmarkhq.ru/english.html?/be_hdd2.html">
<literal>http://www.benchmarkhq.ru/english.html?/be_hdd2.html</literal></ulink>
. Unfortunately most of these are for MS operating systems, but most can
be run from an MS-DOS boot disk.  Note: if you do run one of these
utilities, and it identifies the meanings of any SMART Attributes that
are not known to smartmontools, please report them to the mailing
list.</para>

<para>These utilities have an important role to fill.  If your disk has
bad sectors (for example, as revealed by running self-tests with
smartmontools) and the disk is not able to recover the data from those
sectors, then the disk will <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis>
automatically reallocate those damaged sectors from its set of spare
sectors, because forcing the reallocation to take place may entail some
loss of data.  Because the commands that force such reallocation are
<emphasis role="italic">Vendor Specific</emphasis>, most manufactuers
provide a utility for this purpose.  It may cause data loss but can
repair damaged sectors (at least, until it runs out of replacement
sectors).</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="j">

<title>When I run <emphasis role="tt">smartd</emphasis>,
the SYSLOG <emphasis role="tt">/var/log/messages</emphasis> contains
messages like this:</title>

<programlisting>
smartd: Reading Device /dev/sdv
modprobe: modprobe: Can't locate module block-major-65
</programlisting>

<para>This is because when <emphasis role="tt">smartd</emphasis> starts,
it looks for all ATA and SCSI devices to monitor (matching the pattern
<emphasis role="tt">/dev/hd[a-z]</emphasis> or <emphasis
role="tt">/dev/sd[a-z]</emphasis>).  The log messages appear because
your system doesn't have most of these devices.</para>

<para>Recent releases of smartd can use a configuration file <emphasis
role="tt">smartd.conf</emphasis> to specify which devices to include or
exclude from start-up search.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="k">

<title>What's the story on IBM SMART disks?</title>

<para>Apparently some of the older SMART firmware on IBM disks can
interfere with the regular operation of the disk.   If you have this
problem, a firmware upgrade that fixes the problem is avaialable at
<ulink url="http://www.geocities.com/dtla_update/">
<literal>http://www.geocities.com/dtla_update/</literal></ulink>
.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="l">

<title>How can I check that the package hasn't been tampered
with?</title>

<para>Since the <emphasis role="tt">smartmontools</emphasis> utilities
run as root, you might be concerned about something harmful being
embedded within them. Starting with release 5.19 of <emphasis
role="tt">smartmontools</emphasis>, the .rpm files and tarball have been
GPG signed.  (The tarball's fingerprint is given in the SoureForge
Release Notes.) Please verify these using the GPG Signing Key available
at <ulink url="http://smartmontools.sourceforge.net/SmartmontoolsSigningKey.txt">
<literal>http://smartmontools.sourceforge.net/SmartmontoolsSigningKey.txt</literal></ulink>
.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="m">

<title>Is there a bootable standalone CD or floppy that contains
smartmontools?</title>

<para>If you have a system that is showing signs of disk trouble (for
example, it's unbootable and the console is full of disk error messages)
it can be handy to have a version of smartmontools that can be run off
of a bootable CD or floppy to examine the disk's SMART data and run
self-tests.  This is also useful if you want to run Captive Self-Tests
(the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="tt">-C</emphasis></emphasis>
option of <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
role="tt">smartctl</emphasis></emphasis> ) on disks that can not easily
be unmounted, such as those hosting the Operating System files.  Or you
can use this to run <emphasis role="tt">smartctl</emphasis> on computers
that don't use Linux as the day-to-day Operating System.</para>

<para>At present I am only aware of three such bootable disks:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>LNX-BBC Bootable CD - <ulink url="http://www.lnx-bbc.org/">
<literal>http://www.lnx-bbc.org/</literal></ulink></para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Stresslinux Bootable CD - <ulink url="http://www.stresslinux.org/">
<literal>http://www.stresslinux.org/</literal></ulink></para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>RIP (Recovery Is Possible) Bootable CD/Floppy - <ulink url="http://www.tux.org/pub/people/kent-robotti/looplinux/rip/">
<literal>http://www.tux.org/pub/people/kent-robotti/looplinux/rip/</literal></ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para> Please let us know if there are others, and we'll add them to
this list.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="n">

<title>Can I monitor ATA disks behind SCSI RAID controllers?</title>

<para>From release 5.1-16, smartmontools supports 3ware SCSI RAID
controllers that use ATA disks internally.  To pass commands through the
3ware controller, use the smartmontools <emphasis role="bold">-d
3ware,N</emphasis> option or Directive.</para>

<para>In smartmontools release 5.1-16, the SMART HEALTH STATUS
(smartmontools <emphasis role="bold">-H</emphasis>) is not returned
correctly for 3ware devices.  In this release, the ENABLE AUTOMATIC
OFFLINE and ENABLE ATTRIBUTE AUTOSAVE commands (smartmontools <emphasis
role="bold">-o on</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">-S on</emphasis>)
are <emphasis role="italic">disabled</emphasis> for 3ware devices,
because at the time 5.1-16 was released, the 3w-xxxx driver could not
pass these commands through to the ATA disks.</para>

<para>Later smartmontools CVS code and releases <emphasis
role="italic">do</emphasis> correctly support <emphasis
role="italic">all</emphasis> of these commands.  You may:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Use version <emphasis role="bold">1.02.00.037</emphasis> or
greater of the 3w-xxxx driver, or</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Patch earlier 3ware 3w-xxxx drivers with <ulink url="http://smartmontools.sourceforge.net/3w-xxxx.txt">
<literal>http://smartmontools.sourceforge.net/3w-xxxx.txt</literal></ulink>
so that these commands reach the disks, or</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Use an <emphasis role="bold">unpatched</emphasis> earlier 3w-xxxx
driver (which won't pass these commands to the disks but will instead
print harmless warning messages to SYSLOG).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Since smartmontools 3ware support is new, please report positive
or negative experiences to the mailing list, particularly for 64-bit
and/or big-endian architectures.</para></sect1>

<sect1 id="o">

<title>SCSI disks and tapes (TapeAlert)</title>

<para>smartmontools for SCSI disks and tapes (including medium changers)
is discussed at <ulink url="http://smartmontools.sourceforge.net/smartmontools_scsi.html">
<literal>http://smartmontools.sourceforge.net/smartmontools_scsi.html</literal></ulink>
.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="p">

<title>FireWire, USB, and SATA disks/systems</title>

<para>As for USB and FireWire (ieee1394) disks and tape drives, the news
isn't good.  They appear to Linux as SCSI devices but their
implementations do not usually support those SCSI commands needed by
smartmontools.  The ieee1394 consortium recently certified the first
external enclosure (containing a ATA disk and a protocol bridge) as
being compliant to the relevant standards.  Such devices have already
been on the market for about 3  years and they tend to only support the
bare minimum of commands needed for device operation (i.e. S.M.A.R.T.
support is an unsupported extra).</para>

<para>I'd be very grateful to find someone who could help me test the
smartmontools code on serial ATA (SATA) disks.  They should appear as
normal ATA disks in Linux.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="q">

<title>How does smartmontools differ from smartsuite?</title>

<para>The smartsuite code was originally developed as a Senior Thesis by
Michael Cornwell at the Concurrent Systems Laboratory (now part of the
Storage Systems Research Center - <ulink url="http://ssrc.soe.ucsc.edu/">
<literal>http://ssrc.soe.ucsc.edu/</literal></ulink>), Jack Baskin
School of Engineering, University of California, Santa Cruz.  You can
find some information about the original smartsuite project here:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Press Release 1 - <ulink url="http://www.ucsc.edu/news_events/press_releases/archive/99-00/09-99/smart_software.htm">
<literal>http://www.ucsc.edu/news_events/press_releases/archive/99-00/09-99/smart_software.htm</literal></ulink></para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Press Release 2 - <ulink url="http://www.santa-cruz.com/archive/1999/September/22/local/stories/5local.htm">
<literal>http://www.santa-cruz.com/archive/1999/September/22/local/stories/5local.htm</literal></ulink></para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Press Release 3 - <ulink url="http://www.ucsc.edu/currents/99-00/09-27/smart.html">
<literal>http://www.ucsc.edu/currents/99-00/09-27/smart.html</literal></ulink></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>smartmontools was derived directly from smartsuite.  It differs
from smartsuite in that it supports the ATA/ATAPI-5 standard.  So for
example <emphasis role="tt">smartctl</emphasis> from smartsuite has no
facility for printing the SMART self-test logs, and doesn't print
timestamp information in the most usable way.</para>

<para>The <emphasis role="tt">smartctl</emphasis> utility in
smartmontools has added functionality for this (<emphasis role="tt">-q,
-l selftest,-S, -T, -v and -m</emphasis> options), updated
documentation, and also fixes small technical bugs in smartsuite.  [One
example: smartsuite does not actually use the ATA SMART RETURN STATUS
command to find out the health status of a disk.  It instead tries to
infer this from the SMART Attribute values.]  See <ulink url="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/smartmontools/sm5/CHANGELOG?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain">
<literal>http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/smartmontools/sm5/CHANGELOG?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain</literal></ulink> for a summary of what's been done.</para>

<para>The <emphasis role="tt">smartd</emphasis> utility differs from the
smartsuite <emphasis role="tt">smartd</emphasis> in major ways.  First,
it prints somewhat more informative error messages to the syslog. 
Second, on startup it looks for a configuration file <emphasis
role="tt">smartd.conf</emphasis>, and if <emphasis
role="tt">smartd</emphasis> finds this file, it monitors the list of
devices therein, rather than querying all IDE and SCSI devices on your
system.  (If the configuration file does not exist, then it does query
all IDE and SCSI devices.)  Also, it's a well-behaved daemon and doesn't
leave open file descriptors and other detrius behind.</para>

<para>In addition, the <emphasis role="tt">smartmontools</emphasis>
version of <emphasis role="tt">smartd</emphasis> can be instructed (via
Directives in the configuration file) to monitor for changes in a number
of different disk properties: the SMART status, failure or prefailure
attributes going below threshold, new errors appearing in the ATA Error
Log or the SMART Self-Test Log, and so on. <emphasis
role="tt">smartd</emphasis> can also send an e-mail warning or run a
user-specified executable if it detects a problem with the disk.</para>

<para>The other principle difference is that smartmontools is an
OpenSource development project, meaning that we keep the files in CVS,
and that  other developers who wish to contribute can commit changes to
the archive.  If you would like to contribute, please write to the
mailing-list.</para>

<para>But the bottom line is that the code in smartmontools is derived
directly from smartsuite and is similar.  The smartsuite package can be
found at <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/smartsuite/">
<literal>http://sourceforge.net/projects/smartsuite/</literal></ulink>
.</para></sect1>

<sect1 id="r">

<title>Does it work on Windows?</title>

<para>Currently not, but we consider Cygwin - <ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com/">
<literal>http://www.cygwin.com/</literal></ulink> -  the way to go,
where CVS compiles almost out of the box but still lacks any specific
code to make it work.  Write to the mailing list if you're interested in
porting it.  Someone already sent some S.M.A.R.T. code for Windows,
which may be of use.  Porting to other platforms may be easier as well
now that any Linux specific code (like linux/hdreg.h) has been removed,
and more will be done soon in that direction.</para>

<para>A Cygwin port would probably only require and additional DLL,
cygwin1.dll, to run on plain Windows.</para></sect1>

<sect1 id="s">

<title>Why has the versioning scheme changed?</title>

<para>With the move to GNU Autoconf and GNU Automake it changed from
5.X-Y (where X and Y are one or more numbers) to 5.Y.  This had to be
done because the -Y extension is used by distributions to almost always
denote a new build of the same version. So, the first version with that
change will be 5.19 and not 5.1-19.</para>

</sect1>

</article>
